# 我们即将前往
We are arriving at
# 长发村
"Changfa Cun" ("Long Hair Village")
# 我这个头发和她们比起来
Comparing to their long hair
# 真的就是小巫见大巫
my hair is nothing
# 我的这个才刚多长
Mine is just this long
# 人家那个（头发）好像是说
It's said that their hair can be as long as
# 有一米四
1.4 meters
# （最长1.7米）
# 那真的差不多是一个人的高度了
(Longest is 1.7m)
That's basically as tall as a person
# 哇 头发真的很长
Wow the hair is really very long
# 那么我们这个黄洛瑶寨
So, this "Huangluo Yaozhao" is...
# 黄洛瑶寨
"Huangluo Yaozhai"
(Yao people's village at Huangluo)
# 她们的头发非常长
... their hair is very long
# 刚才我下桥的时候 正好碰到一个导游
I met a tour guide when walking off the bridge
# 他说了一件很有意思的事情
He told me something interesting
# 他说 这边的长发村里
He said that in this long hair village
# 女性老人头发都很长
all elder women have very long hair
# 如果说 女的 前面有一个小揪揪
And if a woman has a "small bun" in the front
# 就是在前面有
I mean, at her forehead
# 有头发 卷起来 盘起来
there's hair twisted into a bun
# 就说明这个女的已经是生过孩子的
that means the woman is a mother
# 很奇特
Very special
# 这是他们这边的习惯 风俗
That's their local custom, or convention
# 感觉好像在探秘一个未知的地方一样
Feels like I'm exploring an unknown place
# 走吧
Let's go
# 买的一个手镯
I bought this bracelet
# 它是这么来的
And that's how it came
# 阿婆可以和你合个照吗
Granny, can I take a photo with you?
# 看您这个头发
I saw your hairstyle
# 头发很特别
Very special hairstyle
# 很漂亮
Very beautiful
# 阿婆 您的头发有多长
How long is your hair, granny?
# 我的头发掉地
My hair can reach the ground
# 掉地上
It reaches the ground
# 这个是生过小孩的
This means I'm a mother
# 这个坨坨
This bun
# 那如果说 不生小孩的呢
Then what if someone doesn't have kids yet?
# 没生小孩的 有个圆圆的
Without kids... They have something round
# 圆圆的
Something round
# 盘在上面的是吧
Oh, twisted at the top, right?
# 盘在上面
Twisted at the top
# 啊
Oh
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 不用谢
You are welcome
# 太可爱了
Adorable
# 光天化日 你们竟然敢
How dare you bath publicly
# 公众在这儿洗澡
in the broad daylight?
# 我这次是跟了一个小团（4人团 6人团这种）
This time I'm in a small tour group
(Like a group of 4 or 6)
# 现在是中午11点多 我们要去吃饭
It's over 11am. We are going to eat
# 不过我发现 这边有很多做竹筒饭的
However, I found a lot of restaurants here serving "Zhutongfan" ("Bamboo Stick Meal")
# 看看有没有机会拍到
See if I we can film it
# （竹筒鸡）
# 每家店都坐满了人
("Zhutong Ji", Chicken in Bamboo)
Every restaurant is full packed
# 我们现在在找
Now we have to look for
# 相对来说 没有那么多人
one that is not so packed relatively
# 但看上去还挺不错的竹筒饭
while still serving some Zhutongfan that looks decent
# 阿婆 这个糯米饭里面有什么
Granny, what are the ingredients with the sticky rice?
# 有香肠 腊肉 胡萝卜 香芋
There are sausages, cured meat, carrot and taro
# - 烤十多分钟就可以了
# - 嗯
- It takes ten minutes or so to cook?
- Yes
# 我不是说 今天本来是报了一个小团嘛
Like I said, we are in a small tour group today
# 然后 给大家看看
And... Let me show the group
# 本来应该要的竹筒饭
the Zhutongfan we originally ordered
# 这么样的竹筒饭
Zhutongfan like this
# 能看清吗
Can you see it clearly?
# 可以（看清）了
Clear now
# （吃不饱 临时点菜）
# 竹筒饭多少钱一个
(Still hungry. Making a hasty order)
How much is a Zhutongfan?
# 28块钱一个
28 yuan for one
# 那种大的是吧
You mean those big ones?
# 竹筒饭外面烤的那种
Those Zhutongfan roasted outside
# 一个回锅肉 再要一个竹筒饭
We ordered a double-cooked pork, and a Zhutongfan
# 多少钱
How much is it?
# 58＋28是吧
58 + 28, right?
# 86
# 还有3块钱的茶位费（餐具、开水、白米饭）
Together with a 3-yuan fixed charge per seat
(tableware, water, rice)
# 先尝一尝他们赠的竹筒饭
Let's try their complimentary Zhutongfan first
# 其实这个竹筒饭就是一节的竹筒饭
This one is just one chunk of Zhutongfan
# 但外面烤的都是一长 一整个的竹筒饭
However, those roasted outside are all long, whole Zhutongfan
# （糯米）有很大的粘性
(Sticky rice) is very sticky
# 里面应该有腊肉吧 能够闻到腊肉的味道
There must be cured meat inside. I smelled it
# 这个就是一共的竹筒饭
This is the complementary Zhutongfan
# （一口一个）
(One bite for one serve)
# 这个是我们自己要的竹筒饭
This is the Zhutongfan we ordered
# 现在把它打开一下
Now let's open it
# 也不多嘛
It's actually not much
# 里面能够看到的就是糯米
We can see there's sticky rice
# 香肠 胡萝卜
sausage and carrot inside
# 这边还是圆柱形
This part is cylindrical
# 咱们把它弄起来
Let's take it out
# 它外面好像是结了一层薄的膜
There's seems to be a thin coating outside of it
# 像烤焦了一样
which feels like burned
# 这是我们的回锅肉
This is our double-cooked pork
# 好 谢谢
OK, thank you
# 不用
Sure
# 这个回锅肉 一上来
At the moment the double-cooked pork was served
# 什么味道都会被回锅肉的青椒味掩盖掉
The fragrance of green peppers in the dish became the only thing you could smell
# 好咸
So salty
# 他们烤的时候 是把竹筒当成锅
When roasting it, they used the bamboo as a cooker
# 把糯米 香肠 胡萝卜都放进去
with sticky rice, sausage and carrot in it
# 烤熟了呢 端上来
When finished and served
# 我们又把竹筒当做碗
we are now using the bamboo as a bowl
# 吃的时候 都不用再弄到碗里
So we don't even need to move the food into a bowl
# 就直接把竹筒当做碗这么来吃
but instead, eat directly with the bamboo as a bowl
# 吃的时候 其实这种糯米的香味
While eating, the flavor of sticky rice
# 还有竹筒的香味
and the fragrance of bamboo
# 都会随着一口竹筒饭
both will follow your bite of Zhutongfan
# 放在口中
and stay in your mouth
# 它这个是事先烤好的
This is roasted in advanced
# 就是你点了之后 它几乎可以立马上
So it can basically be served right after you order
# 外面报的小团嘛 要赶快吃完 赶快走
You know, those small tour group prefer to have a quick meal and then keep on moving
# 拜拜
Bye bye
# （计划：走上观景台 坐缆车返回）
(Plan: climb to the vista point, return in a cable car)
# 哎呀妈呀
Oh dear
# 我们现在爬的最陡的这一部分
We are climbing the steepest part
# 隔一段时间 就会有
Every once in a while
# 奶奶在这边卖东西 劈柴
we may see a granny selling stuff or cutting firewood
# 嗨 你们好吗
Hi, how are you?
# 带上我
Take me with you
# 总算看到希望了 都是小平路了
Finally we are getting there. All flat trails here
# 师傅说 阴天云山雾绕更好看
The guide says the scenery is better in a cloudy day when the moutain is surrounded in the mist
# 但是拍出来可能不太好看
However, that might not be as good in a photo
# 即将到达目的地
Almost at the destination
# 到达山顶
Peaked
# 来 宝贝 看这里呀
Hey baby watch here
# （坐索道返回）
(Take a cable car to return)
# 第一个人 先在第一个位置上跳
The first person jumps from the first spot
# 然后第二个人 还要距他有一定的距离
Then the second person jumps from a few meters away
# 这样 你们才能够上得上去
Only in this way can you get onboard
# 上
Go
# 好 第二个上
Alright, the second person, go
# 第三个上
The third, go
# 最后一个上
The last one, go
# 到我们了
Our turn
# 三号位
Third spot
# 我的妈呀
Oh mama
# 关 注 雪 鱼 探 店
(Subscribe)